你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎来到pwn学院高级漏洞利用模块
welcome to the Advanced Exploitation Module of pwn College
我是Yan，我们将在这个系列视频中整合
I'm Yan and we're going to be putting together in this video series
目前在该课程中学到的所有知识
all of the things you've Learned in the course so far
当然，如果你是碰巧在网上看到这个视频
of course if you are just knowing on this video from the open Internet
下面这个建议可能会让你有点震惊
it might be a bit of a shock
我建议你先学完前面的内容
I would recommend going through all the existing content in the course
因为他们都会在这到达另一个难度
because it all culminates here
让我们开始吧
let's dive in
这个视频是该系列的第一个
this video specifically is going to be the first of a series of videos in which
我们将在该系列尝试攻击启用所有保护机制的多线程服务
we will tackle the exploitation of a multi threaded service with all mitigations enabled
当然，这个服务是有漏洞的
of course the service is vulnerable
我们会把所有的概念组合起来
but we're going to pull together concepts
包括：竞争条件、堆漏洞、ROP等
from race conditions from heap errors from return oriented programming
我们将应对这一挑战
and we're going to tackle this challenge
向你展示攻击它的全流程
and show end to end how you'll exploit that
回想一下我们第一个讲利用场景的模块
if you think back to our first kind of exploitation scenarios module
第一个整合概念的模块
the first putting it together module
有这样一张ppt鼓励你
I have this slide where I encourage you to think like a hacker
在解决挑战题时
when you're approaching hacking challenges
或在分析理解一个系统时，要像黑客一样思考
or a system that you are trying to analyze and understand
有这样一些思考步骤
and there are a number of steps that you undergo
首先拿到一个程序，尝试理解它
first you look at the program understand it
逆向工程、使用它、调试它等等
reverse engineer it interact with it etc
找到一个小的安全瑕疵
then you find the smallest security flaw
想办法利用它
figure out how to exploit it
弄清楚它能提供什么
then you figure out what that flaw allows you
能不能让你理解或者修改目标进程
to understand or change about the running program the process that you're exploiting
或者有其它的用处
and what additional capabilities it gives you
然后利用它带来的能力
then you use those capabilities
重复以上几步
and then you repeat that step
直到攻陷整个系统
until you have this sort of total system compromise
希望你们能用这样的思路
that is the mindset that I encouraged you
解决本模块中所有挑战问题
to approach all of the challenge problems for this module with
在该系列视频中，我们要运用这一思路解决问题
this is the thought process that we're going to try to apply in this video series for this challenge itself
我们来谈谈信息
so let's talk about information
信息是至关重要的
information is critical
如果缺失必要的信息，你所知道的许多技术都无法使用
a lot of the techniques that you know aren't viable without knowing the necessary information
如果不知道程序指令地址，就无法ROP
you can't ROP without knowing where program addresses are
在ROP模块
now in the ROP module
我们已经探讨了找出指令地址的方法
we've explored techniques to figure out where the program addresses are
你得先搞清楚指令地址
but you still need to first figure it out
才能执行ROP链
before you can actually execute a ROP chain
通常情况下，除了某些特定情况
often times except for in certain situations
任何针对堆缓存的攻击，或堆分配重定向
any sort of heap cache poisoning or heap allocation redirection techniques
都需要知道，你要让堆分配在哪里
require knowing where you want the heap to allocate data
或者要知道，堆内存的初始地址
or require knowing where the heap structures are in memory in the first place
为了能获取到这些信息
in order to be able to provide that information
您至少需要知道哪些地址是有效的
you have very at least need to know what data addresses are valid
但理想情况下，您需要知道目标进程的大量信息
but ideally you need to know quite a lot of information about the running process
那么如何最大化利用已知信息
so how do you maximize this information that you know
当然
of course
我们讨论过了一些保护机制
we have talked about a number of mitigations
他们的目的就是让我们无法获知这些信息
that are explicitly aimed at keeping this information away from you
栈金丝雀
stack canaries
在每个栈帧的末尾放置一个未知值
put a unknown value at the end of every stack frame
地址空间布局随机化ASLR
Address Space Layout Randomization
将内存放在随机位置
puts memory in random places
内存区域随机分布在内存空间中
memory spaces in random places in the memory space
比如堆，栈，等等
so the heap the stack and so forth
但是在软件中可能有信息泄露漏洞
but we have information disclosure vulnerabilities that occur in software
我们已经在很多场景见过这类漏洞了
and you've seen a lot of these in different contexts right
在内存错误模块，利用了未初始化内存，泄露金丝雀和地址
you've used uninitialized memory to read out canaries and addresses in the memory errors module
通过tcache泄露出的next，了解堆地址
you have read out tcache addresses to understand where the heap is
在堆，动态分配器安全相关模块
I mean the heap metadata dynamic allocator security module
利用了分配重叠chunk
you've in that module used overlapping allocations
读取并写入你本不应访问的内存
to read and write memory that you weren't supposed to have access to
然后在很多模块中，都有暴力破解地址或者部分地址
and in many modules you've ended up brute forcing addresses or parts of addresses
最终找到正确的值
to get them right
要点是
right so the kind of takeaway is
比如，有一个漏洞能让你劫持执行流
if there's a bug that you can use to hijack Control flow for example
但你不知道要将执行流重定向到哪里
but you don't know where program instructions are to hijack control flow to
这并不是说这个漏洞没用
doesn't mean the control flow bug is useless
只是目前还无法使用它
it just means you can't use it yet
你需要找到更多的信息
and you need to get more information
例如
for example
使用在程序中找到的信息泄露漏洞
using an information disclosure vulnerability that you find in that program
如何发现信息泄露漏洞
how do you find information disclosure vulnerability
一个机智的回答是
well the kind of wise saying of this would be that
一把锤子有两个头
a hammer has two ends
一头可以用来锤钉子
a hammer can hammer in nails
另一头可以用来拔钉子
and it can pull up nails
同样，一个漏洞可能有多种用途
in the same way vulnerability might have multiple uses
你可能用一个漏洞，比如堆溢出漏洞
you might be able to use a vulnerability a heap metadate overwrite
获得重叠chunk后，写内存
to get overlapping allocations and overwrite memory
或者你可以用这个漏洞
or you might be able to use that same vulnerability
获得重叠chunk后，读内存
to get overlapping allocations and read out parts of memory
读出包括像地址、金丝雀等本来无法读出来的内存
including addresses canaries etc that you might not supposed to have access to
一般来说，在做这个的时候
in general as you're doing this
你要持续追问一些问题
you have to keep track of what your current mental state is
你对目标程序有多少了解
what you know about the program that you're trying to exploit
你对目标进程有多少了解
what you know about the process
当前你要利用的运行着的程序实例
the specific instance of that program that's running that you can exploit or
有哪些之前运行获得的，并对当前进程有用的信息
what you know about previous iterations of that process that would still apply to this process
例如，内存中的相对布局
relative layout in memory for example
要多问自己还有没有能找到的有用信息
you need to keep track of what you need to know which you need to find out
并多想想能做什么
and you need to keep track of what you can to do
要活用这些信息提供给你的工具
you need to understand what are the tools available at your disposure
如果拿到了一个锤子，别忘了锤子的另一头
don't forget if you have a hammer you might have the other end of a hammer
你也可能要用它来拔钉子
you might have the nail puller as well
也许有个更好的名字
there's probably a better name for it
我们来看一个例子
we're going to look at this as a motivating example
我把它分在两张ppt上了，一张放不下
I spread across two slides because it won't fit on one side
这里只是网络设置的代码
this is just the network setup code
它是一个多线程服务器
it is a threading server
在main里，它只是启动并监听1337端口
in main it just starts up and listens on port 1337
来一个连接，他就创建一个线程
and for every new connection it creates a thread
它在每个线程中调用handle_connection来处理
it invokes the handle_connection handler in every thread
这里用FILE对象来装文件描述符，是因为
thus wraps the file descriptor in a file object for
这样可以使用 fprintf 和 fscanf 等函数
so that we can use fprintf and fscanf and so forth
然后调用一个有漏洞的函数
and then calls the vulnerable function
这是个样板
this is all boilerplate
任何多线程服务都可以套用这个
could be any service that's threading could use the same thing
一个建议是，是否有用取决于你的规划，
in fact one useful thing in your life depending on where you go from here
建立一套可以快速使用的C模板代码库
is having like sets of these sort of templates in C that you can really quickly grab
要是需要一个多线程服务器
you need a threading server
ppt上的代码随便用
feel free to grab this slide
然后实现这个vuln函数
implement the vuln function
希望你写的函数没有漏洞
hopefully yours won't be vulnerable
除非你想让它有，然后利用它
unless you want it to and go for it
好吧，不管怎样，真正的有意义的是什么
all right anyways so what is the actual meat
这是实际的服务代码
here's the actual service
看起来应该很熟悉
and it should look pretty familiar
这简直和babyheap一模一样
this is almost exactly babyheap
几乎和动态分配器误用模块的挑战题模板完全一样
almost exactly the challenge template from the dynamic allocator misuse
但有一个重要的不同点
with one massive difference
它是安全的
it's secure
它实时记录着messages各元素的分配情况
right it actually keeps track of whether or not the messages are allocated
在babyheap的那些挑战题中
so if in babyheap in those challenges
你把messages地址放在这个数组中，当时称为allocations数组
you allocated messages into this allocation array there was called allocations
把分配地址放到这个allocations表中
so you allocated stuff into the allocations table
等free时
and then when you freed it
程序不将指针清零
it didn't zero out the pointer
你可以利用那个指针
and you could mess with that pointer
解引用它，然后操纵里面的数据
dereference the pointer and mess rather with the data inside it
随意修改堆缓存的元数据
with the heap caching information as much as you wanted to
在这里你不能
here you can't
当我们申请分配时，只会在
when we allocate it will only do the allocation
这里没有分配过时，分配
if there isn't something allocated in that entry of the messages table
然后它会实时记录目前哪些分配过了
and then it'll keep track of what it has allocated so far
free时也一样
and likewise for deallocation
只有在分配状态时，才执行free
it'll only do the deallocation if there isn't an entry there
它也会持续记录目前已经释放的
and it'll also keep track of what it has deallocated so far
当然，它也对溢出做了保护
and of course it also protects against overflows
它最多只读取已分配内存的大小
it will only read the size of the allocation
至少输入到堆上时没问题
at least on the heap
在写入前，它会检查确保已经分配了内存
it will check to make sure that you actually have something allocated before it writes it there
以单线程的角度看，挺安全的
it seems pretty secure in a single threaded way
显然，这里仍然存在一些缺陷
obviously there are still some flaws here
一个例子是，这个input有缓冲区溢出
one for example is there's a buff overflow in the input
你能向这个程序发送任意长的输入
so you can send any length of input to this program
你能触发一个栈缓冲区溢出
and you can do a stack buff overflow
但它是一个多线程服务
but it's a threading service
一旦破坏栈金丝雀，服务就崩了
the moment you hit that canary that service is dead
因此，在单线程方式下，你无法利用此漏洞
so in a single threaded way you would not be able to exploit this
但是在多线程中，就不一样了
but in multi threading all bets are off
这个服务中不同线程运行的代码依赖了很多
basically this service has a lot of dependencies between code that is running in different threads
全局变量
and global variables that that code uses that are in global memory
它在线程之间是共享的
that is shared between threads
而且没使用互斥锁
and not guarded by mutexes
这意味着存在竞争条件
right this means that there are race conditions
蓝色箭头代表这个依赖关系
the blue arrows are any data dependency that
会导致不走if分支，走else（有的话）
disables something that is pointing to
如果这个stored[idx]等于0成立
so if this stored equals 0 happens
如果我们free了它
so if we free an allocation
我们将无法写入到messages数组（光标指错了）
then we will no longer be able to write into this messages array
红色的这些箭头，将导致走if分支
the red ones the red arrows enable things
如果stored[idx]等于1，就可以free
so if stored is equal to 1 then we'll be able to free
当然，在单线程中，就像我说的，这是安全的
now of course in a single thread like I said this is secure
但在多线程场景中
but in the multi threaded scenario
这里以及世界上大多数的计算机服务
in which we and most of the rest of civilized computer science operates
都会有问题
there are going to be problems
下个视频我们将深入一步
next video we're gonna dive into the first step
利用这些问题，攻破整个程序
of leveraging these problems toward the compromise of this whole program
到时见
see you there